For Lucien,
it all began with ink,
paper and the love of beauty.
LOST ILLUSIONS
Orphaned and destitute,
he was obliged
to learn a trade to survive.
His sister Eve had married
an Angouléme printer
and he worked
in their modest shop,
dreaming of another life.
THE MARGUERITES
POEMS
Even today in Paris,
people wonder how
his story could have happened,
what movement of the world
swept him away.
Here.
- I'll be late.
- No, you won't.
They won't eat you alive.
But for now, this long alleyway
transported him to a new world,
almost another country...
All the way to
Madam de Bargeton's chateau.
The guests are arriving, My Lady.
Thank you.
Enduring a husband
almost as old as her chateau,
she considered herself
a patroness of the arts.
One Sunday after mass,
the bishop spoke of a young poet,
a worker at a printer's,
who went by the prestigious name
of Lucien de Rubempré.
The most difficult
is to render
the vitality of the petals.
You see the eglantines?
Please leave.
For her.
Thank you, Lucien.
This is a great honor.
| feared you might not come.
Your husband's here?
Don't be silly.
He only reads hunting treatises
and plays with his dogs.
You're very beautiful, madam.
My dear friends,
| thank you for your loyal presence.
One day perhaps,
our protégé will be recognized
and famous,
and we shall be able to say:
"| knew him,
and his work moved me."
Last month, our young poet read us
a magnificent biblical poem.
Our gazette
hailed him in glowing terms:
"When dazzling talent
emerges in a great youth,
"it is fresh hope for us all.
"A new springtime in one's life.
"Only 20,
but the force of an artist."
For him, poetry is holy,
almost a personal religion.
One can only revere minds
in whom God has placed His light.
Sir, we are waiting.
Your satchel, it's unbecoming.
For her.
Love,
prayer
and song,
to me existence gave.
Of all the earthly good
that mortals crave,
In this my farewell hour
| nought regret.
Nought, save the burning sighs
that soar above,
The lyre's full ecstasy,
or wordless love
Of hearts that ne'er forget.
To sweep the lyre
at listening beauty's feet,
To mark from note to note
the transport sweet,
Thrill her rapt bosom
with responsive power
To draw tears of rapture
from her eyes
As morning dews are swept
by zephyrs' sighs
From the full, bending flower.
Forgive me.
They have narrow lives,
they feel nothing.
It was very beautiful.
Excuse me.
Marquise de Contades
wishes to thank you, madam.
What do you expect from them?
And you?
What did you think?
One does not think these things,
one feels them, right?
Louise.
Such a love
as you have made me feel,
| thought both utopic and forbidden.
Forbidden,
like all which
must in the end triumph.
Each word
brings your lips closer,
each book | read
seems to speak of you.
Since this dreadful afternoon,
I've thought only of you.
Of you, alone in the shadows
of those lifeless walls,
loveless and without poesy.
Nothing but love
matters in this world.
And love is like the wind...
it will carry us away.
For you, Louise,
Lucien.
She took irrational risks to meet him,
inventing reasons to run off.